so the five hindrances sensual desire
aversion that lazies
drowns in a sloth sloth
restless agitation and
doubt
so how to overcome those things how to
well i think the
the first point to make is
to clear up what those hindrances are
not because i think the contemporary sort of
because i think the contemporary sort of
buddhist meditators take on the
hindrances it's actually quite
it's actually quite mistaken
most people would have a notion that you
know hindrances are these things that sort of
hindrances are these things that sort of
uh arise occasionally in me
and uh oh and my mind is fully kind of
focused on the last order version that's
the hindrance of life to the version
it's not that's the result of the
hindrance of last version and so on
hindrances in themselves are pretty much
on the on that
like on the level of of your currently
enduring existence as a whole
so as a basis for your world it's a
hindrance so only in jhana mind is free from
so only in jhana mind is free from
hindrances
only when when the when the samadhi has
been developed to the extent of jhana
mind has overcome hindrances
everything else even your day-to-day
life even if you're not
necessarily gripped by last diversion or
doubt you are within the domain of the
hindrances
so they're they're they're on the level
pretty much
um of of your existential situation and
by that i mean
at any given time you are either lustful
or liable to lust you're either
irritable or liable to irritation you're
either lazy distracted or liable to those
lazy distracted or liable to those
things to manifest
same goes with the agitation and body or
liable to education and worry
and doubtful or liable to doubt
so in other words it's not that there's
like these five hindrances one two three
four five fundamentally you're within the
five fundamentally you're within the
domain of
the five as one thing in the same sense
you have the five aggregates
and then on account of the five
aggregates you have to discern single
out one of them
at a time if you if that's what you
discern and
focus your attention on well the
hindrances is the same principle
it's the five hindrances is your basis
the basis of an unenlightened
undeveloped mind
is the domain of the five hindrances and
then they are exemplified and manifested
they are exemplified and manifested
through one of them at the time or the
liability of one of them through the
time that's why surmounting the hindrances
that's why surmounting the hindrances
equals surmounting the world
in the first jhana
so it's surmounting the entire existing
situation whereby
now you are
withdrawn now you're safe not just from
lust but from
liability to the future loss that has
also been
abandoned and same goes for hate
and all the other hindrances so the
reason why this is important is because
for as long as people think hindrances
are these things then come and go
all you need to really do to deal with
them is just manage the state while it's
there but if you actually start
understanding that
no hindrances are on the level of my
situation already as it is even if i
don't discern any specific hindrance
that's already within the hindrance
that will now force you to broaden the
context more and more and more and more
until you reach that supreme shore of
safety from hindrances that's in the
first genre
not because these things don't arise
like the buddha doesn't say
um abandoning the five hindrances
surmounting the joys and griefs in
regard to the world he doesn't say
joys and grief doesn't arise in regard
to the it means you surmount it means
it's there
the domain of joys and griefs and five
hindrances is there
but you have surmounted it not like oh i
have no no
no issues no hindrances arising for me
thus i'm entering the jhana
no that's well within the domain of the
hindrances so the five is really the one the one
so the five is really the one the one
gateway as we always speak
through which these five different
examples of it exemplifications would
then come and become more particularized
and when the students talk about you
know the temporary liberation from the
hindrances yeah there are many different ways you
yeah there are many different ways you
can understand what temporary means as
in like all this moment i'm hindrance
this moment i'm not hindrance thus i'm
temporarily free from hindrance
or you can also understand it as you can
surmount the domain of the hindrance of the five
the domain of the hindrance of the five
hindrances regardless of which one
is there for you the most but you
surmount the gateway of the five
and you have surpassed them you are free
from them but
if you become negligent if you don't
cultivate and protect that gateway
you will fall back into the domain of
the hindrances so you lost your
temporary liberation
or your liberation was indeed temporary
so the gateway well the gateway the five
yeah so that that's
you have to start thinking on the level
of that gate the peripheral context oh
the gateway of the five
is why i get lust here anger there doubt
yesterday fear tomorrow not because those things
fear tomorrow not because those things
are the actual hindrances
they're just examples of that domain
that you live in and that's often like
you would say my domain one way would be
to to
reflect is there as a brute is there a
reason lust in me
can the non-reason lust arise so not
just oh what's what's here right now
but what is not here right now that
could be right here right now
last anger so that liability you start
to include
as a hindrance already because i might
not have any central design now but am a
liable yes
means hindrance of sensuality is there
it's a foolish thing to think that oh
because it's not here right now when i
focus i don't see any last time free
from it
are you liable yes means the hindrance
is there liability
is part of the hindrance oh i don't know
well so is the hindrance of doubt and lack of
so is the hindrance of doubt and lack of
clarity there oh yeah
yeah so i don't know if i if i'm liable
to lust
am i am i not but i'm liable to doubt
i don't know well if you don't know
you're liable to last means you are yeah
because the only time to not be liable
to last is to be clear about liability
the last that you have abandoned
but if you're liable to one of those
hindrances well
then you're in the domain exactly one
hindrance means the basis of the five is
there that's why it's always the five
hindrances when the buddha speaks about
the five nibaranas not three and a half
or two
it's always the five and these are the
five ways does
the five would show itself to you so to
speak and would harass you and overwhelm
you and that's why often like the arahants
and that's why often like the arahants
liberation the iron
development of mindfulness often goes
handed to he's he's the one
who destroyed the hindu samantha of the
hindrances of the fire
so the level of surmounting of the
hindrances is the level of surmounting
of the world which is the basis for
radahanship so if you start thinking of them instead
so if you start thinking of them instead
of these individual things that
occasionally come your way but start
seeing them as as basically
your world is within the five hindrances
your sense restraint is within the five
hindrances your dhamma practice is
within the five entrances
only time to not be within the five
entrances is in the first jhana
that's why the one who has samantha
entrances then dwells in abides
abides in that vacant it's seclusion
from unwholesome states
and what they said whether he walks sits
down eats
whatever goes to the toilet everything
is divine everything is safe because
he's withdrawn from it
so the first step to withdraw yourself
from it is to see them for what they are
not to think just managing occasional
like irritation or doubt a little bit of
doubt is i'm dealing with the hindrances
you need to see it on the level of the
context that you're already within that
liability to them means they're there
otherwise you wouldn't be liable to them
you start thinking like that then you
can get to like well eventually
depending on you know how much effort
you put in how much clarity you develop
but you get to see that you are responsible
you get to see that you are responsible
you're not responsible for hindrances
arising but you're responsible for them
hindering you
you are the one that basically takes
them up
ignorantly one way or the other but it's
not on the level of the choice
as i say often it's not like you choose
to take and now you just have to choose
to not take it
it's more like sometimes you choose to
do something that then results
in you being unable to not take them
so if you stop thinking of them
individually but see them as one
then doesn't matter what hindrance is
there your attitude towards the
the any hindrance that's where you start
looking for although in lust i can't
read with the suba in anger or country
with mata i'm just managing these
spontaneous little states that have
arisen for me
no it doesn't matter whether it's last
diversion delusion distraction fear
worry unwholesome state is present what
is your mental attitude in regard to
that so in a way you could practice freedom
so in a way you could practice freedom
from hindrances by practicing
the discernment of liability to the
unwholesome of any kind
don't matter if it's five or more
whatever because that's what they'll
have in common by the way
so why are you then liable to
unwholesome states
why can't you just not be pressured by
well the answer is quite simple because
some of the unwholesome states you don't
see as unwholesome
and you willingly entertain them
delight in them welcome them act out of
them the gateway we spoke about you know
the gateway we spoke about you know
that's the game but sometimes you
willingly turn a blind eye to the gateway to the
turn a blind eye to the gateway to the
extent you're able to ignore the gateway
to that extent
the hindrances will still find the way
in
and what is the chief hindrance on
account of which
people then let all the other four in
so to speak its sensuality not seeing
the danger in sensuality
means not seeing the danger in the basis
of five hindrances
and because of that when the worry when
the hindrance that you don't want comes
you will not be able to remain
surmounting it you will be involved
because your practice up to that point
was involvement with the hindrances by
choice to welcoming sensuality in your thoughts
to welcoming sensuality in your thoughts
delighting it in your thoughts
and above all not seeing the danger the
peril of it
and that's by the way where the crux of
that recognition also is
the danger the danger in sensuality is
not that
later on you know things will not work
out or it will be too much to manage
thus sensuality is not really good
the danger of even before you engage in
sensuality the danger of not seeing the
danger in sensuality is the danger of implicit
in sensuality is the danger of implicit
fort waiting to come with the dam
with this with the fifth centrality so
through willingly delighting in
sensuality you're willingly accepting
anxiety worry fear threat sluggishness
worry fear threat sluggishness
lack of energy depression everything
else that comes through the hindrances
your way
and if you recognize that oh the danger
becomes apparent that's the immediate
danger in the prospect of sensuality we're not
in the prospect of sensuality we're not
talking about the results of sensuality
are dangerous
before you engage with centrality
sensuality is dangerous
which is if a monk understands that or a
person understands it they will
not want the centrality and that's the
simile of the burning embers in the pit
not knowing the danger of it you enjoy
burning yourself with it
the moment you understand the danger
then your mind will be
turning everywhere else except to that
it doesn't that's the only place he
doesn't want to be in
so seeing the connection between
welcoming sensuality
and the implicit weight of the danger
that's hidden in that welcoming
of all the five that can overwhelm your
mind to the point of madness
you realize oh no my sincerity is worth
accepting the risk
so the danger becomes apparent and
that's the similar like you know
keeping your head on the chopping block
would be basically centrality
because it's comfortable you know props
your neck in the right right angle it
relaxes your muscle is great it's very
very agreeable
but it implies a waiting axe to drop
it's a chopping block and the
the the axe and the parallel that will
come with it
is basically the other four that are
inseparable from the chopping block
that's why again people don't see a
connection between the perils that they are exposed
between the perils that they are exposed
and they can see
and the entrance for those perils
through their acceptance of sensuality
because if they do there's again as they
would have said the danger will become
apparent so the only reason they don't see that
so the only reason they don't see that
and they keep engaging with reality
because there is no apparent danger
and that's why the first genre often the
simile of the pleasure of the genre it's
just always described in terms of relief from
always described in terms of relief from
the danger
like crossing the desert you don't know
if you survive then you come out and you
survive being released from the jail
come back alive your home even better
paying the debt
back and now you're safe it's always the
sense of safety
so the sense of safety is not not having
anybody knocking on your door
threatening to you or
experiencing worry or the sense of
safety is not welcoming sensuality
through which no liability of other
hindrances can apply to you
and above like the reason why this is so
so great and wholesome is because
you realize it's entirely up to you
welcoming sensuality or not it doesn't
depend on the circumstances like oh you
know i'm not lucky it's just these things
i'm not lucky it's just these things
coming my way i can't say no
you can always say no to welcoming
sensuality and the level of your
thoughts you have thoughts of sensuality
but what is your attitude oh this is
agreeable friendly
dear to me not dangerous entertaining
or this is the entrance for basically
the eons of samsara and suffering that
comes with it
welcoming of sensuality
so that's when practically speaking
always the other four hindrances
will torment you there's only so much
you can control in terms of your
circumstances and avoid sooner or later
things will come up internally
worry anxiety depression whatever else
all of that
is because you do not see the peril of
the centrality you don't see the danger
of the you don't see bait
as a bait see sensuality comes up you
don't recognize the bait
of it or you don't see the hook inside
of it
and that's what the hook is there's no
like oh yes you know like on the level
of
psychologization yeah sensuality every
time i engage with it you know it's not
really afterwards you don't feel that great so
afterwards you don't feel that great so
it's better that's that's fine but it's
on the level of psychology that will not
uproot things
they will just you know convince you
maybe to restrain a bit more
but for uprooting of sensuality
uprooting of the gateway of the other
four hindrances for uprooting of the domain
hindrances for uprooting of the domain
of the five
you need to see the apparent inherent
implicit parallel waiting before you
even engage not in
after you engage and that's why always
sensuality was compared to like a bait
different types of bait
poisonous drink that you don't know it's
poisonous the hunter sets up the bait
for the deer the eats gets gets
trapped because he didn't see the bait
that's on the level of the thoughts when
you have thoughts of centrality you need
to start seeing them
as bait and that's how then you will
become unable to welcome it you can't just
unable to welcome it you can't just
choose to not welcome sensuality
that's impossible but if you contemplate
the danger in it as the buddha would say
then you realize your welcoming will
start to fade
because the only reason you used to
welcome it because you never saw what it
implies right there and then not later
right there and then not later
and that's why the danger becomes
apparent you understand the extent of
gratification and then you understand
the extent of escape
you know exactly oh if i keep
contemplating the danger
the gratification which is my welcoming
and delighting in the prospect of it
will fade
and that will be the thorough escape
from this
so the abandoning of the hindrances is
done through you basically preventing
through you basically preventing
yourself
from welcoming certain aspects of those
hindrances because of which
you are then subjected to all of them
the effort you make in in protecting
them one guard
doorway you realize oh no you're free
from all of it and that relief is your
energy now
your alertness everything comes out of
it as opposed to
i'm so tired today i can't even think
straight because i'm overwhelmed by the
fatigue i'm overwhelmed by the worry all of that
i'm overwhelmed by the worry all of that
overwhelms you burdens you
hinders you narrows down your context
your peripheral when it doesn't matter
how much you practice it because
why because you're still liable to it
why because you're still not seeing the
peril of central thoughts
and don't confuse seeing the parallel of
central thoughts with not having central
thoughts that's not the same thing you're going
that's not the same thing you're going
to have central thoughts or other
thoughts the word sensuality
and that's where you see the peril but
it doesn't mean you have no thoughts of
centrality rising anymore and the
significance of central joy has
disappeared no that state that's why you surmount it
no that state that's why you surmount it
not you prevent it from arising
then if you have surmounted it for a
long period of time
it will eventually even stop arising on
its own not because you stopped it
so again this
the lighting and sensuality or valuing
pleasure sense pleasure not seeing the
danger in it implies already value of
of the pleasant experience that this
offers so you
very much so when you get anger
and getting angry you know if you get
angry because you're irritated
it's painful situation and that prospect
of getting angry getting rid of
the displeasure is also a
because you value it the pleasure that
comes from even if people don't want to
get angry even if they say
anger is bad i don't want to get angry
you will get angry
because mentally your mind will accept
the offer of anger as a hindrance
because your mind has been accepting the
offer of centrality
and saying when the doubt arrives you
will be unable to remain unmoved in the
face of doubt
it doesn't matter how much you would
wish to be unmoved your mind will be
gripped by the doubt because that's the
that's your mother being you've been
taking up the hindrances
by taking them one you're taking up the
fire
but like as you can see in each
hindrance there's this value of pleasure
exactly that's what i mean like instead
of dealing with this hindrance like this
this is start seeing what's in common to
any hindrance
wholesomeness of it the implicit value
of of
getting rid of the discomfort so that's
another reason why
you get pressured into taking it well
you get pressured and then you choose to
accept the pressure and then you take it
you keep but yes the pressure of
sensuality is unpleasant that's why
you take it because not just you free
yourself from that displeasure first but
on top of it you get more pleasure
through the sense object
you know you are hungry and you want to
eat the mangoes
and that's the simile of the deer herd
that i often go the deer
are factually hungry they need to eat
but the difference is whether you learn
how to eat everything but
the bait or whether you see no
difference and then either eat everything or try to
and then either eat everything or try to
not eat anything
and either way of those those examples
that the buddha gave us deer hurt were
caught by the deer by the deer hunter
so as i say you don't have to worry
about the four hindrances
just worry about the one that is always
the gateway for all the other four which
is sensuality
doesn't matter i'm an angry type i'm a
slow type i'm a sluggish type
all of that means you're essential type
you're the type with the lights you're
the type of delight
in the in the kind of in the manner
that then allows all these other
hindrances to proliferate
expand and and so on
that delighting pleasure means that
you're going to be not delighting
in pain which means you're going to be
going for pleasure
and so and it's like so you get
entangled even more and more yeah
you start seeing the danger in
delighting in the prospect of pleasure
that in itself is not painful that's a
neutral neutral thing
getting pleasure not getting pleasure is
the level of pain
seeing the danger before you engage with
pleasure it's not painful
it's eye-opening but you need to work
your way to that level to see
there because for as long as you think
the hindrances
are the objects of your attention oh i
got essentiality now i've got this ill
will now
you're not it's nowhere near where
they're rooted so you're not going to be
dealing with anything you're just
managing and covering it up
so that's what i mean existentially
you're always within the hindrances
sensory strain prevents you from
proliferating further but your mind is
still within them
so don't think you're safe because
there's no sensuality arising
if you think you are safe you ask
yourself well can the non-reason
centrality rise do i see a connection do
i see
how that will not affect me even if it
happens and no idea so you have no idea how to
and no idea so you have no idea how to
escape the five entrances and yet here
you are practicing meditation for your
genres yet the jhanas are once you surmount the
yet the jhanas are once you surmount the
hindrances
he summons the hindrances the uh the
joys and griefs in regard to the world
and griefs in regard to the world
anything basically they might narrow
your context
then abides in that then the pleasure of
seclusion of that
is what the jannah comes out of but as i
say often people think
give me a technique i'll enter the
special experience that i will call
jhana i will believe it's a jhana and then
i will believe it's a jhana and then
these hindrances will stop arising for
me
and joys and griefs of the world will
not come my way
it's other way around you surmount the
500 says
you overcome joys and grief so that's
the work
and then the safety you get is the
pleasure of the jana then you just need
to maintain and protect
so you see why people would like
meditation technique meditation
experience everything else falls off because the
everything else falls off because the
implicitly no that's where the work is
so if i get the janna my work is done
for me
as opposed to i do the work which is far
more unpleasant
and for as long as you cultivate that
kind of view you will get nobody in
practice doesn't matter what special
experiences you have